Philip Lee Phillips Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Philip Lee Phillips Papers 1885-1921
MSS59923
Phillips, Philip Lee, 1857-1924
200 items
4 containers
1.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Cartographer and chief director of maps of Library of Congress Map Division. Correspondence, writings, printed matter, and other personal material relating to Phillips’s work and career at the Library of Congress as a cartographer and chief of the Library’s Map Division.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Phillips, Philip Lee, 1857-1924.; Putnam, Herbert, 1861-1955--Correspondence.
Organizations
Library of Congress--Officials and employees.; Library of Congress. Library of Congress archives.; Library of Congress. Map Division.
Subjects
Cartography.; Map collections--Washington (D.C.)
Occupations
Cartographers.; Librarians.
Provenance
The papers of Philip Lee Phillips, cartographer and chief director of maps of the Library of Congress Map Division, were given to the Library of Congress by John Jameson, assistant secretary for the Smithsonian Institution, in 1981.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Philip Lee Phillips are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Born in Washington, D.C., March 1, 1856, Philip Lee Phillips was raised in New Orleans and Georgia before returning with his family to Washington in 1866. His father, Philip Phillips (1807-1884), served in the House of Representatives from South Carolina before the Civil War and practiced law there afterwards, including before the Supreme Court as a prominent local attorney. Phillip Lee Phillips entered Columbia College Law School in 1874, but left school a year later for a position on the staff of the Library of Congress. In 1879 he was listed as an official cataloger. Prior to that, his salary had been paid without his knowledge by his father. He soon developed an expertise in cartography, leading to an appointment in 1897 as superintendent of the Hall of Maps and Charts in the new Library of Congress building and in 1906 as chief of the Maps and Charts Division. In 1899 Phillips married Imogen D. Hutchins. He produced numerous bibliographies and atlases, including the first lists of maps and atlases in the Library of Congress, where he was employed at the time of his death on January 4, 1924. Among his principal works were A List of Geographical Atlases in the Library of Congress (4 vols., 1909-1920) and Lists of Maps of America in the Library of Congress (1901).
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Philip Lee Phillips (1857-1924) span the years 1885-1921 and consist of correspondence, writings, printed matter, and other personal material focused on Phillips’s work and career at the Library of Congress as a cartographer and chief of the Library’s Map Division. Almost entirely letters received, the correspondence is mostly from government officials, libraries and cultural institutions, bookstores, and publishers pertaining to his atlases and bibliographies and to his employment at the Library of Congress. Prominent among the correspondents is Librarian of Congress Herbert Putnam.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Letters retrieved from the apartment of Phillips, Washington, D.C., 1887-1917 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Dodd, Mead and Co., 1918 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Phillips, 1892-1915 (Box 1)
    - A-K, (5 folders) (Box 1)
    - L-Z, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Writings by Phillips (Box 2)
  - “Bladensburg in the British Peerage: How It Happened” (Box 2)
  - “Bernard Romans: His Biography and Bibliography with a Reproduction of the ‘Two Whole Sheets Maps’ of Florida, 1774” (Box 2)
    - Copies (Box 2)
    - Drafts (Box 3)
    - Notes (Box 3)
- Miscellany (Box 3)
  - “An Account of the Life and Character of Christopher Ludwick” (Box 3)
  - Biography of Daniel Smith (Box 3)
  - “Coachman of the Marquise” (story translated from French) (Box 3)
  - Cuba (Box 3)
  - Division of Maps and Charts, Library of Congress (Box 3)
  - Estrada Palma, Tomás (Box 3)
    - Testimony to the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations (Box 3)
    - Representing himself to the delegate plenipotentiary and general agent aboard, of the Cuba Republic to the secretary of state (Box 3)
  - “History of Tennessee” (Box 3)
  - Letter of L. A. Nuckols, 1908 (Box 3)
  - Letter to Emmons from W. A. Baillie-Grohman (Box 3)
  - Maps (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Printed works of William Tatham, letters to Governor Randolph (Box 3)
  - “Royal Ordinances concerning the Laying out of Towns” (Box 3)
- Printed matter (Box 4)
- Mounted printed matter and clippings, (3 folders) (Box 4)